(Hammer)
(مطرقة)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Microwave beeps) (Laughter)
(صوت مايكروويف) (ضحك)
You probably all agree with me
قد تتفقون جميعا معي
that this is a very nice road.
أن هذا طريق جيد
It's made of asphalt,
مصنوع من الإسفلت
and asphalt is a very nice material to drive on,
و الإسفلت مادة يسهل القيادة فوقها
but not always, especially not on these days as today,
و لكن ليس دائما، على الأخص ليس في الأيام الشبيهة بهذا اليوم
when it's raining a lot.
عندما تمطر السماء بهذه الشدة
Then you can have a lot of splash water in the asphalt.
و تكثر المياه المتناثرة على الإسفلت
And especially if you then ride with your bicycle,
و خصوصا إذا كنتم تقودون الدراجة الهوائية
and pass these cars, then that's not very nice.
و تمر تلك السيارات بجواركم و هو أمر غير جميل
Also, asphalt can create a lot of noise.
و يمكن أيضا للإسفلت أن يصدر الكثير من الضجة
It's a noisy material,
إنه مادة كثيرة الضجة
and if we produce roads like in the Netherlands,
و إذا بنينا طرق كما في هولندا
very close to cities, then we would like a silent road.
قريبة جدا من المدن، حينها سنرغب بطرق صامتة
The solution for that is to make roads
و الحل هو صناعة طرق من
out of porous asphalt.
إسفلت مسامي
Porous asphalt, a material that we use now
الإسفلت المسامي هو مادة مستخدمة حاليا
in most of the highways in the Netherlands,
في أغلب الطرق السريعة في هولندا
it has pores and water can just rain through it,
و تحتوي على مسامات يمكن لمياه المطر أن تتسرب خلالها
so all the rainwater will flow away to the sides,
و بالتالي ستتدفق كل مياه الأمطار بعيدا إلى الأطراف
and you have a road that's easy to drive on,
مما يمنحنا طريقاً يسهل القيادة عليه
so no splash water anymore.
و بالتالي نتخلص من المياه المتناثرة
Also the noise will disappear in these pores.
كما ستختفي كل الضجة في هذه المسامات
Because it's very hollow, all the noise will disappear,
لأنها مجوفة تماما، كل الضجة ستختفي
so it's a very silent road.
إذا هي طرق صامتة جدا
It also has disadvantages, of course,
و بالطبع لديها عيوب
and the disadvantage of this road is that raveling can occur.
و عيب هذا الطريق هو إمكانية حدوث التطاير
What is raveling? You see that in this road
ما هو التطاير؟ يمكن أن نلاحظ في هذا الطريق
that the stones at the surface come off.
تفكك الحجارة الموجودة على السطح
First you get one stone, then several more,
بدءاً بحجر واحد يتبعها المزيد من الحجارة
and more and more and more and more,
و المزيد و المزيد و المزيد و المزيد
and then they -- well, I will not do that. (Laughter)
و ثم ... حسنا, لن أفعل ذلك (ضحك)
But they can damage your windshield,
لكن يمكن أن يتحطم و يتعرض لتعرية الرياح
so you're not happy with that.
الشيء الذي لن نكون سعداء به
And finally, this raveling can also lead to more and more damage.
و أخيراً، هذا التطاير سيقود للمزيد و المزيد من الضرر
Sometimes you can create potholes with that.
أحيانا يمكن أن تتكون حفر بسببه
Ha. He's ready.
ها، إنه جاهز
Potholes, of course, that can become a problem,
حفر، بالتأكيد هذه يمكن أن تصبح مشكلة
but we have a solution.
و لكننا نملك الحل
Here you see actually how the damage appears in this material.
هنا يمكن أن نرى كيف يظهر الضرر في المادة حقيقة
It's a porous asphalt, like I said, so you have only
إنه إسفلت مسامي، كما قلت، و بالتالي سيتواجد فقط
a small amount of binder between the stones.
كمية صغيرة من الإسمنت بين الحجارة
Due to weathering, due to U.V. light, due to oxidation,
بسبب التجوية، بسبب الأشعة فوق البنفسجية، بسبب التأكسد
this binder, this bitumen,
هذا الإسمنت، هذا القار
the glue between the aggregates is going to shrink,
الصمغ الذي يربط بين المجاميع سيتقلص
and if it shrinks, it gets micro-cracks,
و إذا تقلص ستحدث شقوق مجهرية
and it delaminates from the aggregates.
و ستتظى المجاميع إلى طبقات رقيقة
Then if you drive over the road, you take out the aggregates --
و حينها عند القيادة على الطريق ستتلف المجاميع
what we just saw here.
و هو ما شاهدناه هنا
To solve this problem, we thought of self-healing materials.
لحل هذه المشكلة فكرنا في مادة ذاتية المعالجة
If we can make this material self-healing,
إذا تمكنا من جعلها ذاتية المعالجة
then probably we have a solution.
حينها فقط قد نحصل على حل
So what we can do is use steel wool just to clean pans,
و بالتالي ما يمكننا ان نفعله هو استخدام سلك الغسيل الخاص بتنظيف الأواني
and the steel wool we can cut in very small pieces,
و بتقطيع هذا السلك إلى قطع صغيرة
and these very small pieces we can mix to the bitumen.
و خلط هذه القطع الصغيرة بالقار
So then you have asphalt
حينها سنحصل على إسفلت
with very small pieces of steel wool in it.
يحتوي على قطع صغيرة من سلك الغسيل داخله
Then you need a machine, like you see here,
بعد ذلك سنحتاج إلى آلة، كالتي ترونها هنا
that you can use for cooking -- an induction machine.
يمكن أن نستخدمها للطهي -- آلة تحريض
Induction can heat, especially steel; it's very good at that.
التحريض يرفع حرارة المواد و على الأخص الفولاذ، إنه ممتاز
Then what you do is you heat up the steel,
و بالتالي ما سنفعله هو أننا سنرفع درجة حرارة الفولاذ
you melt the bitumen,
سنذوب القار
and the bitumen will flow into these micro-cracks,
و سيتدفق القار السائل في الشقوق المجهرية
and the stones are again fixed to the surface.
و يتم إصلاح الحجارة مرة أخرى و إلى السطح
Today I use a microwave because I cannot take
اليوم استخدمت المايكروويف لأنه لا يمكنني إحضار
the big induction machine here onstage.
أداة التحريض الضخمة هنا على المسرح
So a microwave is a similar system.
إذا المايكروويف مشابه للنظام
So I put the specimen in, which I'm now going to take out
و لذلك وضعت العينة فيه، و الآن سأخرجها
to see what happened.
لنرى ما الذي حدث
So this is the specimen coming out now.
و ها هي العينة
So I said we have such an industrial machine in the lab
و قد قلت أن لدينا مثل هذه الآلة في المعمل
to heat up the specimens.
لرفع حرارة العينة
We tested a lot of specimens there,
و قد اختبرنا العديد من العينات هناك
and then the government, they actually saw our results,
وعندما رأت الحكومة نتائجنا
and they thought, "Well, that's very interesting. We have to try that."
قالت "حسنا، هذا مثير للاهتمام. يجب أن نجربه"
So they donated to us a piece of highway,
و هكذا تبرعوا لنا بجزء من الطريق السريع
400 meters of the A58, where we had to make
400 متر في الطريق A58، حيث كان علينا أن ننفذ
a test track to test this material.
مسار اختبار لهذه المادة
So that's what we did here. You see where we were making the test road,
و هذا ما فعلناه هنا. يمكنكم أن تشاهدونا عند اختبار الطريق
and then of course this road will last several years
و بالتأكيد هذا الطريق سيظل لعدة سنوات
without any damage. That's what we know from practice.
بدون ضرر ، هذا ما تعلمناه من الممارسة
So we took a lot of samples from this road
و قد أخذنا مجموعة من العينات من هذا الطريق
and we tested them in the lab.
و أخضعناها للاختبار في المعمل
So we did aging on the samples,
قمنا باستهلاك هذه العينات
did a lot of loading on it, healed them with our induction machine,
أخضعناها لأعباء عالية، عالجناها باستخدام آلة التحريض
and healed them and tested them again.
عالجناها و اختبرناها مجددا
Several times we can repeat that.
و أعدنا الاختبار عدة مرات
So actually, the conclusion from this research is that
فكانت النتيجة من هذا البحث كالآتي
if we go on the road every four years
إذا عاودنا هذا الطريق كل 4 سنوات
with our healing machine -- this is the big version
بآلة التحريض -- هذه نسخة كبيرة
we have made to go on the real road --
صنعناها لتستخدم على طريق حقيقي --
if we go on the road every four years
إذا عاودنا هذا الطريق كل 4 سنوات
we can double the surface life of this road,
يمكننا أن نضاعف عمر سطح هذا الطريق
which of course saves a lot of money.
مما سيوفر بالتأكيد الكثير من المال.
Well, to conclude, I can say
حسنا، لنلخص يمكن أن أقول
that we made a material
أننا صنعنا مادة
using steel fibers, the addition of steel fibers,
باستخدام النسيج الفولاذي، زيادة النسيج الفولاذي
using induction energy to really
و باستخدام طاقة التحريض
increase the surface life of the road,
لزيادة عمر سطح الطريق
double the surface life you can even do,
حتى مضاعفته
so it will really save a lot of money with very simple tricks.
و بالتالي توفير الكثير من المال بحيل بسيطة
And now you're of course curious if it also worked.
حتما الآن أنت تتساءلون إن كانت تعمل حقاً
So we still have the specimen here. It's quite warm.
حسنا، ما زلنا نملك العينة هنا، إنها دافئة قليلاً
Actually, it still has to cool down first
في الحقيقة، يجب أن تبرد أولاً
before I can show you that the healing works.
قبل أن استعرض عليكم النتائج العلاجية
But I will do a trial.
و لكنني سأقوم بمحاولة
Let's see. Yeah, it worked.
لنرى. نعم، إنها تعمل
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
تصفيق